<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-31T01:03:27+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rehmat Singh Chawla</title><subtitle>Welcome to my website! I study Physics, make coffee, write poetry and generally vibe. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Call out to me once more</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Call-out-to-me-once-more/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Call out to me once more"/><published>2024-08-28T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-28T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Call%20out%20to%20me%20once%20more</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Call-out-to-me-once-more/"><![CDATA[<p>As I obtained my degree and left IIT Bombay for what might be the last time as a student, I struggled to reach the sadness through the sheer surrealness of the idea. I may be back someday, briefly, but I will be different, and so will the people. The endless days spent on those roads are now at an end. I’m still trying to process this, and so I turned, as I often do, to poetry:</p> <div class="poem"> <b>Call out to me once more</b><br/><br/>O rows of desks and lecture halls,<br/>Call out to me once more<br/>O empty roads and rambling walks,<br/>Call out to me once more<br/>O noisy score from room next door,<br/>Call out to me once more<br/>O tree-rimmed lake-edged home off home,<br/>Call out to me once more.<br/><br/>O hours spent slogging, arduous days,<br/>Interspersed with coffee breaks<br/>Rants erupted, tea was spilled<br/>A camaraderie most singular built<br/>O baubled ceilings, nights of vice<br/>Company till crack of light<br/>Through sanguine love and pardoned hate<br/>We forged these friendships ‘spite of fate<br/><br/>O petrichor and sunset-smote<br/>O rooftop scenes and days of birth<br/>O frenzied clicks and lectures slow<br/>O laughs familiar and smiles adored<br/>O haunted rooms and vaunted halls<br/>Give me reason to come home<br/>O memory-laden mud and walls <br/>Call out to me once more.<br/></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I miss college, the campus and the people.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I don’t read anymore</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Why-I-don't-read-anymore/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I don’t read anymore"/><published>2024-08-20T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Why%20I%20don&apos;t%20read%20anymore</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Why-I-don&apos;t-read-anymore/"><![CDATA[<p>A friend once coined the phrase “Bibliophile (non-practicing)” to describe us grown-up bookworms — but as everyone around me has gotten over the slump, I still struggle to make time for what was my most treasured hobby just 7-8 years ago. So I wrote about it, as I do.</p> <div class="poem"> <b>Why I don't read anymore</b><br/><br/>My bookshelf stands at my bedside, a hundred titles a stretch away<br/>It’s been there for years, but what were once rows familiar<br/>Are now adorned with twenty spines unknown, and thirty more I call “to be read”<br/>How did I go from stroking the pages<br/>To reaching only for the phone charger among them?<br/>Or else the perfume on the top shelf<br/>People and reels now consume my days<br/><br/>Before I could pocket a screen, I hungered for words<br/>On the way back from the bookstore<br/>Half a sentence per streetlamp<br/>That flashed through the car window<br/>And dinner, and the bus, and the dance lessons I could not care less for<br/>All dedicated to the words and the worlds within<br/><br/>I ache to go back<br/>But I also don’t<br/>Because the chef in me itches to see more recipes<br/>The quizzer in me desires to hoard more facts<br/>The linguistics nerd in me wants more etymology<br/>The coffee <s>addict</s> aficionado seeks a better brewing technique<br/>Born with the personal computer, I’m passionate about the power of these machines and of a world that exploits them fully<br/>A romantic, I can never have enough of hope, prose or poetry<br/>And having known friendship, who could go back to solitude?<br/>So it goes<br/>Always a book with me, scarcely opened<br/>Its words and worlds, to me unknown<br/>Mostly a ghost, haunting me<br/>With the me who has now grown to be more<br/><br/>He still lives, the hungry kid<br/>Comes to visit, every now and then<br/>He never stays long<br/>But the bookmark still moves<br/></div> <p>The poem doesn’t talk about the future, or about hope. I couldn’t fit it in there. But I do still hope that I’ll be back someday. Someday I’ll curl up with a book and not realise the sun went up or down, and I’ll get up with a sore back, insane hunger and an unpennable satisfaction of having finished an emotional rollercoaster. I can’t wait.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Regards, a non-practicing bookworm]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To Complain of Undersea Rain</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/To-Complain-of-Undersea-Rain/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Complain of Undersea Rain"/><published>2024-08-11T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-11T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/To%20Complain%20of%20Undersea%20Rain</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/To-Complain-of-Undersea-Rain/"><![CDATA[<p>There is an inherent contradiction between poetry being my solace from my worries and my pride that I promote shamelessly — sometimes, I need to write about people who will read the poems. xD<br/>And so, this poem resulted — nonsense to all who read it, and by now, even to me.</p> <div class="poem"> <b>To Complain of Undersea Rain</b><br/><br/>Obvious are my words to my life’s many know-it-alls<br/>So I’ll rant without meaning as I wax metaphorical<br/>There’s plenty to weigh me, so I’ll be categorical<br/>Just note, any pleas to you to understand are rhetorical<br/><br/>"1 and 2 I don’t adore! But-" talks 3 and walks 4<br/>And -2 looms large and new<br/>Like an infinite sum times 24<br/>But 24 or 26, no alphabet can be my fix,<br/>Count down char and count up tar<br/>But concrete remains elusive<br/><br/>On to nicer problems now<br/>Spectacles I can’t live without<br/>Spectacles next to spectacles gleam<br/>Spectacles glint in spectacled dreams<br/>Empty pockets beg for use<br/>Earphones do the job of two<br/>Nicer problems Netflix stream<br/>While I drown under Willie’s steam<br/><br/>Sense this lacks, and intended so<br/>But take this solace ere I go<br/>If in some eons I open this file<br/>(I pray) this makes yet littler sense to you and I</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A nonsense poem - I hope]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I live for stories</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/I-live-for-stories-prose-version/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I live for stories"/><published>2024-07-17T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-17T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/I%20live%20for%20stories%20-%20prose%20version</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/I-live-for-stories-prose-version/"><![CDATA[<div class="tba"> (Warning, this is more of a prose piece.) </div> <p>Self-identity is always a nebulous concept, and one I’ve struggled with a fair bit. But occasionally I will write a piece that crystalises many of my broodings about my idea of self. This is one of them.</p> <div class="poem"> <b>I live for stories</b><br/><br/>Bidding goodnight to the table, I swung my bag onto my back and hopped off the raised platform of the roadside Chaayos and begun the walk back to my room. But as I put on my spectacles, an unusual figure came into focus - my course professor, with whom I’d had an enlightening discussion on tangent spaces in manifolds that very morning. He looked at the table I had just left, laughing uproariously in the dead of night, and back at me. “Is this how you live? How absurd.” He said, judgingly. “Are you surprised, because you thought I was a dedicated student?” “Or else you would be napping in the backbenches in my class, if you were gallivanting with this crowd all night.” I shook my head. “Maybe you’re guessing based on certain people you’ve seen, who live for the fun, the ruckus and the parties. Maybe you thought I live for my work, and the ambitions that drive me. I live for neither of those.” “Then what do you live for?”<br/>The poetry I told him then, I’ll tell you word for word.<br/>“I live for stories. The ones you raise glasses to, or whisper furtively. The ones told at nighttime with eyes bleary, the gossip you save for afternoon tea, the dinnertime tall tales and the anecdotes exchanged over coffee.<br/>I live for stories, so I read like possessed (and occasionally, watch movies). I visit worlds galore and return exhilarated or teary, and I keep wanting more. Maybe I’ll write one myself, we’ll see.<br/>I live for stories. In Physics I find the stories of the world I’m exploring, and in Maths the stories my kind write to make sense of things, and when I find the sense too much to make sense of, I turn to writing out the nonsense in my head into poetry.<br/>I live for stories, and people are not so much characters, but rather bundles of stories. So I keep all my kin, and I listen with intent, because everyone has tales to tell, places they’ve been and things they’ve felt. I judge a wardrobe by its tshirts, not the dress shirts that bay for glory.<br/>I live to tell stories - be a storyteller - turns out there’s a performer in me. When I hold the stone I’ll spin tall tales to leave you amazed and dumbstruck and mortified (sorry). And so in everything in my life I seek stories, and every day of mine I could make a story, and when there’s a choice so bold it’d make a story worth being told, then I make it, and it’s risky, but I’ve got the devil’s luck with me.<br/>I live for stories. And secretly, I dream of being a story - living a life worth talking about, a legacy worth posterity. Therein lies my drive, the ambition that pushes me. And there’s decades to go and many false starts to forgo, but one day I’ll be a story - one others dream to be, or one they read themselves to sleep.”<br/></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><category term="prose"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A homage to my many reasons to love life]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rap and Poetry</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Rap-and-Poetry/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rap and Poetry"/><published>2024-01-17T08:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-17T08:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Rap%20and%20Poetry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Rap-and-Poetry/"><![CDATA[<p>I’d been writing the occasional poem for a long time when I discovered rap music, and at first I did not draw a connection between the two. But less than an year later, when I penned my first rap (for a Chemistry assignment, no less), I realised how similar it was to when I used to write poetry. This motivated me to pick up the pen again - more seriously this time - and led to the most bountiful era my poetry has seen.<br/> I’ve realised that my works often have dual qualities allowing for rap-like readings as well as poetic performances, and I want to explore this further. In response to the occasional dissenting opinions, I composed the following piece - and well, I’ll let it speak for itself.</p> <div class="poem"> <b>Rap and Poetry</b><br/><br/>Some would like to draw a line between rap and poetry<br/>I would like to live where they would dig the pit<br/>I’ll straddle the line with devices and disses<br/>Hop over it and back like I’m skipping to a beat.<br/>My power lies in my pen, and it can’t be taken from me<br/>I’ll write lyrical epics and literary rhapsodies,<br/>Something which could be sung to a crowd with a beat, or appreciated as an artistic symphony.<br/>As interdisciplinary as can be<br/>That’s the only way I can ink me.</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The two rhythmic genres are considered disjoint by many, but I want to explore their intersection.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prisoner of my mind</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Prisoner-of-my-mind/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prisoner of my mind"/><published>2024-01-16T17:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-16T17:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Prisoner%20of%20my%20mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2024/Prisoner-of-my-mind/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>Prisoner of my mind</b><br/><br/>O prisoner of my mind, what raven-song you sing?<br/>A mockery, a tragedy, of quests to find my wings<br/>You’d have me play the clipper, my company the cage<br/>And not satisfy till you have me drowned, in sorrow or in rage<br/><br/>Imprisoner of my mind, what command you to-day?<br/>That I should lash unjustly, or whelm and lifeless stay?<br/>That I should starve, insomniate, or sloth my while away?<br/>Do what you will, but do to me, drive not my friends astray<br/><br/>Master of my mind, what lessons do you bring?<br/>Tell tales of my fallacies, so hate may seep in<br/>I’ll stab me till I’m mastered, so hand me, if not blade,<br/>Shards from the mirrors I would shatter to be great</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Would life not be a cakewalk if I could listen to myself?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I walk away</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/I-walk-away/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I walk away"/><published>2023-12-21T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-21T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/I%20walk%20away</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/I-walk-away/"><![CDATA[<p>Ambition has always driven me to do more and be more, but there have been a few unforgettable moments in my life when I realised it is simply not enough. Time runs out. You sacrifice, or you compromise. And sometimes you must walk away.</p> <div class="poem"> <b>I walk away</b><br/><br/>They smile and wave, all dressed up<br/>A Friday night, so the agenda<br/>Is to take a break, dance the night away<br/>I walk up the hill to where equations lay<br/><br/>They call my name, and slow me down,<br/>Music sounds, a band’s in town,<br/>I stop, and ponder, turn around,<br/>"Sorry guys, I’ll sit this one out."<br/><br/>And I walk away<br/>And I wish I’d stayed<br/><br/>Cheers and groans follow answers<br/>They practice, it’s triumph they’re after<br/>Home, out of place, I’m guilt and mistakes,<br/>I should atone, work longer, learn faster<br/><br/>And I walk away<br/>And I wish I’d stayed<br/><br/>Suitcases line the bus stop<br/>Last-minute checks and rushed walks<br/>"There’s an empty seat," they say to me<br/>But I just stick around till they drive off.<br/><br/>And I walk away<br/>And I wish I’d stayed<br/>And I wish I could stop, and take a break<br/>Could stay with the people I ache to be with<br/>Give them more than seconds snatched in haste<br/>But I run each day, and I get nowhere,<br/>And if I stop, a failure stay<br/>So I walk away<br/>I refuse to stay<br/>My ambition’s tall<br/>And discipline frail<br/>All I’ve got is this stubborn denial of pain<br/>So I’ll exploit it again and again till I’m great</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ambition demands sacrifice]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fragile</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Fragile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fragile"/><published>2023-09-16T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-16T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Fragile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Fragile/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>Fragile</b><br/><br/>Fragile<br/><br/>I'm a glass trophy balanced on the top shelf<br/>You see me shine, reaching high, face etched into a smile<br/>I see the fall, unstable, wobble to the edge<br/>And it scares me, because I know I'm fragile<br/><br/>I'm a Jenga tower 20 minutes into the game<br/>Surrounded by Nerf wars unknowingly played<br/>Shots tugging emotions into knots and braids<br/>A tangle that pins me to the mess I've made<br/><br/>Pitiful, weak, I'm unhardened, I know<br/>I should be above it, these thoughts come and go<br/>But to find me a machete it's taking a while<br/>And the vines pull me now, when I'm just too fragile</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[FragileFragileI'm a glass trophy balanced on the top shelfYou see me shine, reaching high, face etched into a smileI see the fall, unstable, wobble to the edgeAnd it scares me, because I know I'm fragileI'm a Jenga tower 20 minutes into the gameSurrounded by Nerf wars unknowingly playedShots tugging emotions into knots and braidsA tangle that pins me to the mess I've madePitiful, weak, I'm unhardened, I knowI should be above it, these thoughts come and goBut to find me a machete it's taking a whileAnd the vines pull me now, when I'm just too fragile]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grocery Store Breakdown</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Grocery-Store-Breakdown/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grocery Store Breakdown"/><published>2023-09-16T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-16T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Grocery%20Store%20Breakdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Grocery-Store-Breakdown/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>Grocery Store Breakdown</b><br/><br/>There's bread, and cheese, and coffee, and me,<br/>Holding back tears next to aisle number 3<br/>Fumbling through feelings, can't forgive the me<br/>Who's standing in the way of all I want to be<br/><br/>The sunset's a poached egg sitting low in the sky<br/>But for belle sights I'm too rotten, a little cracked, kinda fried<br/>Beats pounding my head, used to make me feel alive,<br/>Now just mushy, kinda soupy, served up with some chives<br/><br/>Tripping on cobblestones, wishing to hurt,<br/>I stumble into pizza, some coffee, dessert<br/>And the street comes alive with twinkles and glee<br/>Turns out I just needed dinner to be me</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hunger at the core of the human condition]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bad With Words</title><link href="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Bad-With-Words/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bad With Words"/><published>2023-08-23T17:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-23T17:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Bad%20With%20Words</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rehmatschawla.github.io/blog/2023/Bad-With-Words/"><![CDATA[<div class="poem"> <b>Bad With Words</b><br/><br/>Bad with words<br/><br/>I’m bad with words<br/>You may be surprised,<br/>A poet claiming he doesn’t know how to write?<br/>It’s not so much my vocab, or the grammar being right,<br/>But making my words mean what I want them to mean<br/>My light-absorbing orbs stare down the blinking line, black on white<br/>I can’t tell if I should delete to the left or write to the right<br/>Emails not worth minutes have taken me nights<br/><br/>Emails, yes, that’s where people say they don’t know what to say,<br/>But say, you want C to do B by time A,<br/>Then so you say, make it a little polite, send and be on your way<br/><br/>That’s not the hard part, but oh, if I start to say what’s hard I’ll never get anywhere<br/>Mostly because I’d stick a TWSS into any conversation I’m near<br/>(TWTS?)<br/>But also because I’m bad at saying things so that you hear what I want you to hear<br/><br/>Let me break it down, I suck at conversations, I think too slow and miss my chances,<br/>Laugh too much, and when I do empathise I seem unresponsive<br/>Unresponsive when asked for opinion or advice,<br/>And when I respond I doubt every word I say<br/>(Though that’s a story for another day)<br/><br/>I’ve never added value to conversations, lest I can twist them to myself<br/>I talk too much about myself, well<br/>It is the only subject I know kinda well<br/>But then it comes back to the well of all the ways I’m bad with words<br/>To beg for a job you gotta overwhelm and convince them of your worth<br/>And I lack the words to make me worth a dwell - or maybe just lack faith in my worth?<br/><br/>Well, this has been far too many words without much worth<br/>You’re welcome to leave now, apologies for keeping you long<br/>TWSS<br/>Sorry, couldn’t resist<br/>Maybe I could have if I had something more worthwhile to say<br/>But I’m just that bad with words.<br/></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'm supposed to be good with language, as a poet and avid reader. But I don't always feel that way.]]></summary></entry></feed>